A Guide to the Record Group Vertical Files, 1960s-present
Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech
- Record Group 48 - College of Liberal Arts and Human Sciences (CLAHS)
  - RG 48/4 - Department of English
    May include the Steger Poetry Prize; Center for Rhetoric in Society; Creative Writing Program; Visiting Writers Series; Fowler-Giovanni Fund
    See also RG 15/10.
  - RG 48/5 - Department of History
    History courses have been offered since 1872 under various names and organizations: English, History, and Political Economy, 1891-1898; English, History, and Spanish, 1898-1902; History, 1902-1906; History and Economics, 1906-1916; Economics and History, 1924-1957; courses offered through Business Administration Department, 1957-1961; History and Political Science, 1961-1965; and History, 1961-present. The Department of History moved from the College of Arts and Sciences [RG 15/13] to the College of Liberal Arts and Human Sciences in 2003.
    See also RG 15/13.
  - RG 48/6 - Department of Religion and Culture
    Moral philosophy courses had been offered as early as 1872 and religion courses since 1954. The Department of Philosophy and Religion [RG 15/21] was formed in 1955. The department split in July 1983 into the departments of Philosophy and of Religion. In 1994, the Department of Religion became the Religious Studies Program in the Center for Interdisciplinary Studies [RG 15/27; RG 38]. At some point, Religious Studies merged with the Judaic Studies Program [RG 15/26] and Appalachian Studies [RG 42]]. In July 2003, the department moved from the College of Arts and Sciences to the College of Liberal Arts and Human Sciences as the Department of Religion and Culture.
    May include Appalachian Studies Program; Appalachian Studies Conference; Malcolm and Diane Rosenberg Program in Judaic Studies
    See also RG 15/21; RG 15/26; RG 15/27; RG 38; RG 42.
  - RG 48/7 - School of Performing Arts [items also in Oversize Box 2]
    Music courses were first offered in 1965 and theatre arts courses in 1967. In 1970, the Department of Performing Arts and Communications (PAC) [RG 15/15] formed with courses in theatre arts, music, and communications. PAC split into three departments: Music, Theatre Arts, and Communication. In 1983, the departments of music and of theatre arts combined into the Division of Performing Arts [RG 15/15/3c]. The Division joined with the Department of Art and Art History [RG 15/3] to form the School of the Arts in the College of Arts and Sciences.
    In July 2003, the College of Arts and Sciences dissolved, and the School of the Arts became cross-collegial when the Department of Art and Art History moved to the College of Architecture and Urban Studies (CAUS), while the other departments joined the College of Liberal Arts and Human Sciences (CLAHS).
    In 2008, the Department of Art and Art History separated from the other departments to become the School of Visual Arts [RG 14/10] in CAUS. The Cinema program developed in the Department of Communication [RG 48/3] but later separated from Communication and joined the departments of Music and of Theatre Arts as the School of Performing Arts and Cinema. This was renamed the School of Performing Arts in 2013.
    May include Performances/plays sponsored by school or by students and faculty; Theatre 101; Virginia Tech String Project; Summer Arts Festival; Linux Laptop Orchestra (L2ork); Virginia Tech Honor Band; Trumpet Festival; International Day of Collaborative Music
    See also RG 15/15; RG 15/15/3c; RG 48/3.
  - RG 48/8 - Department of Human Development and Family Science
    The Department of Human Development was previously housed [RG 15/30] in the College of Arts and Sciences [RG 15]. The Department was renamed the Department of Human Development and Family Science in Fall 2017.
    May include Little Hokies Day Care; Child Development Center for Learning and Research; Marriage and Family Therapy Program at the Northern Virginia Capital (NVC); Adult Day Services; Neighbors Growing Together program
  - RG 48/9 - School of Education
    A Department of Education [RG 15/29] was founded in the College of Arts and Sciences starting 1965, and the College of Education [RG 17] was established on July 1, 1971. In 1996, the College of Education merged with the College of Human Resources to form the College of Human Resources and Education [RG 19].
    May include Training and Technical Assistance Center (T/TAC) [see also RG 19/11]; Elementary Education
    See also RG 15/29; RG 17; RG 19.
  - RG 48/10 - Department of Apparel, Housing, and Resource Management
    In 2003, the College of Arts and Sciences (CAS) dissolved and the College of Liberal Arts and Human Sciences (CLAHS) was formed. The Department of Apparel, Housing, and Resource Management moved from from CAS [RG 15/30] to CLAHS at that time. The department developed out of Housing, Interior Design, and Resource Management [RG 19/8] in the College of Human Sciences and Education [RG 19].
    May include Center for Real Life Design
    See also RG 15/30; RG 19/8.
  - RG 48/11 - Department of Sociology
    Rural sociology courses were offered as early as 1872. Since that time, sociology courses have been offered under the following departments: Agricultural Economics and Rural Sociology, 1929-1933; Agricultural Economics, 1933-1940; Agricultural Economics, Rural Sociology, and Statistics, 1946-1948; Agricultural Economics and Rural Sociology, 1948-1965; Psychology and Sociology (1965-68); and Sociology, 1965-1968; and Sociology, 1968-present. The department moved from the College of Arts and Sciences [RG 15/19] to the College of Liberal Arts and Human Sciences in 2003.
    May include Criminology; Africana Studies; Hip Hop Studies; Women's and Gender Studies; American Indian Studies; Center for Peace Studies and Violence Prevention [RG 48/16]
    See also RG 15/19.
  - RG 48/12 - Department of Science, Technology, and Society (STS) [items also in Oversize Box 2]
    The Department of Science and Technology in Society was renamed to the Department of Science, Technology, and Society (STS) in Fall 2017.
    May include Science and Technology Studies; Nicholas C. Mullins Lecture; Choices and Challenges Forum
  - RG 48/13 - Department of Modern and Classical Languages and Literatures
    Foreign language courses have been offered since 1872 under different names and organizations: Latin, 1873-1887; English and Latin, 1887-1891; English, History, and Spanish, 1898-1902; English and Spanish, 1902-1903; Modern Languages and Latin, 1915-1920; Foreign Languages, 1920-1958; English and Foreign Languages, 1958-1965; and Foreign Languages, beginning 1965. The Department was later renamed Foreign Languages and Literature. The department moved from College of Arts and Sciences [RG 15/10] to the College of Liberal Arts and Human Sciences [RG 48/13] in 2003. In Fall 2017, it became the Department of Modern and Classical Languages and Literatures.
  - RG 48/14 - Department of Philosophy
    Moral philosophy courses had been offered as early as 1872. The Department of Philosophy and Religion [RG 15/21] was formed in 1955. The department split in July 1983 into the departments of Philosophy and of Religion. In July 2003, the department moved from the College of Arts and Sciences to the College of Liberal Arts and Human Sciences.
    May include Program in Philosophy, Politics, and Economics
  - RG 48/15 - Department of Political Science
    Courses in political economy were first offered in 1875. The different names and organizational structures that political science courses have been offered under include English, History, and Political Economy, 1891-1898; English, History, and Spanish, 1898-1902; History, 1902-1906; History and Economics, 1906-1916; Economics and History, 1924-1957; Business Administration, 1957-1961; History and Political Science, 1961-1965; and Political Science, 1965-present. The department moved from the College of Arts and Sciences [RG 15/16] to the College of Liberarl Arts and Human Sciences in 2003.
    May include International Studies Program; Pre-Law
    See also RG 15/16.
  - RG 48/16 - Center for Peace Studies and Violence Prevention
- Record Group 49 - Virginia Tech - Wake Forest University School of Biomedical Engineering and Sciences (VT-WFU SBES)
  Formed in 2003, the Virginia Tech - Wake Forest University School of Biomedical Engineering and Sciences (VT-WFU SBES) is an interdisciplinary graduate program combining the resources of the Wake Forest School of Medicine, the College of Engineering at Virginia Tech, and the VA-MD Regional College of Veterinary Medicine.
  May include Helmet ratings and concussion research; Brain cancer research
  See also RG 18/18; RG 20/3.
  - RG 49 - Virginia Tech - Wake Forest University School of Biomedical Engineering and Sciences (VT-WFU SBES) (Information and Publications)
- Record Group 50 - Division of Information Technology
  Created in 1983, Computing and Information Systems [RG 5/9] was renamed Information Systems [RG 6/14] in 1986. In 2002, the division became Information Technology.
  See also RG 5/9; RG 33/2.
  - RG 50 - Division of Information Technology (Information and Publications)
    May include IT Procurement and Licensing Solutions
  - RG 50/1 - Vice President of Information Technology and Chief Information Officer (CIO)
    Created in 1983, the Vice President for Computing and Information Systems [RG 5/9] was renamed Information Systems [RG 6/14] in 1986. In 2002, the position became the Vice President for Information Technology, with Chief Information Officer added to the title in 2009.
  - RG 50/2 - Individual Faculty and Staff
  - RG 50/3 - Advanced Research Computing (ARC)
    May include HokieSpeed; System X; Supercomputing
  - RG 50/4 - Information Technology Security Office (ITSL)
    May include Virginia Cyber Range; Cybersecurity; Virginia Cyber Cup; Phishing scams
  - RG 50/5 - Enterprise Systems
    May include Ellucian Banner
  - RG 50/6 - Network Infrastructure and Services (NI&S)
    May include Internet; Communication Network Services; University telecommunications
  - RG 50/7 - Secure Identity Services
  - RG 50/8 - Technology-enhanced Learning and Online Strategies (TLOS)
    May include Scholar Learning Management System; Canvas Learning Management System; XCaliber Award; 4-VA Course Development Grants; Accessible Technologies; Design and Develop Awards; Networked Learning Initiative (NLI); InnovationSpace / Innovation and Outreach Studio
  - RG 50/9 - IT Experience and Engagement
    May include 4Help
  - RG 50/10 - Collaborative Computing Solutions (CCS)
- Record Group 51 - University Ombuds Office
  The University Ombuds Office was created in November 2018.
  - RG 51 - University Ombuds Office (Information and Publications)
  - RG 51/1 - Director of the University Ombuds Office
    The position of the Director of the University Ombuds Office was created in November 2018.